<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Don&#39;t Blame The Data</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Don&#39;t Blame The Data</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Agony and the Ecstacy of my first open source contribution</title>
      <link>/blog/first-open-source-contribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/first-open-source-contribution/</guid>
      <description>For the last year or so, I’ve had this desire to contribute to an open source R package, but like a lot of people, I found the thought of tackling the task frightening.
While I work in a really dynamic and close team every day, and in the world of remote repositories (Git), I’ve had really limited exposure to collaborative working in these remote repositories… We tend more to work on projects largely on our own, so the concepts of pull requests (PRs), merging, forking… well it was all a bit daunting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysing AFL Team Age... Properly!</title>
      <link>/blog/analysing-afl-team-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/analysing-afl-team-age/</guid>
      <description>After seeing my beloved Hawthorn Hawks tweet out an article on their website regarding player ages for each team, it got me riled up that the media love to cite Champion Data’s “average age” as their measure.
As can be seen with the age distribution of players as at the start of the 2020 AFL Premiership Season, the figure is going to be skewed by the older players on lists, especially with guys like Shaun Burgoyne, Kade Simpson, Gary Ablett Junior…</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All roads lead to gganimate</title>
      <link>/blog/all-roads-lead-to-gganimate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/all-roads-lead-to-gganimate/</guid>
      <description>This post aims to introduce you to animating ggplot2 visualisations in r using the gganimate package by Thomas Lin Pedersen.
The post will visualise the theoretical winnings I would’ve had, had I followed the simple model to predict (or tip as it’s known in Australia) winners in the AFL that I explained in this post. The data used in the analysis was collected from the AFL Tables website as part of a larger series I wrote about on AFL crowds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effectively Simplifying AFL Tipping</title>
      <link>/blog/simplifying-afl-tipping/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/simplifying-afl-tipping/</guid>
      <description>I feel like I always overthink footy tipping. During each round, I make myself believe I have some sort of secret sauce and conjure up visions in my head of nailing a solid roughy… and then fall flat half way through the season and give up…
So then I thought, surely there’s an easier way. Only problem was, I thought this up last weekend (during the last season of the round)…</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How the narrative changed after the Boomers&#39; win</title>
      <link>/blog/how-the-narrative-changed-after-the-boomers-win/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-the-narrative-changed-after-the-boomers-win/</guid>
      <description>On the 24th of August, 2019, the Australian Men’s Basketball team, the Boomers, created history when they were able to enact their own David and Golliath moment, taking down Team USA for the first time ever. More impressively was the fact that the US hadn’t lost a game in 13 years. It was a marvelous moment in Australian basketball history, and while the US fielded what is widely considered one of their weaker teams, it was a moment for us to all savour.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An In Depth Analysis of FIFA 19</title>
      <link>/blog/an-in-depth-analysis-of-fifa19/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/an-in-depth-analysis-of-fifa19/</guid>
      <description>This post was originally released on the Kaggle FIFA 19 Complete Player dataset that was kindly collected by Karan Gadiya. Many thanks Karan. The link to my original kernel is here
The full code base can be found here
Introduction From Wikipedia:
 FIFA 19 is a football simulation video game developed by EA Vancouver as part of Electronic Arts’ FIFA series. Announced on 6 June 2018 for its E3 2018 press conference, it was released on 28 September 2018 for PlayStation 3, PlayStation 4, Xbox 360, Xbox One, Nintendo Switch, and Microsoft Windows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tribute to Jarryd Roughead with some obscure data</title>
      <link>/blog/a-tribute-to-jarryd-roughead-using-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-tribute-to-jarryd-roughead-using-data-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Jarryd Roughead - four-time Hawthorn premiership player and all round great man - formally announced his retirement this week, with his last game coming over the weekend against the Gold Coast Suns.
Not only was he a pivotal four-time premiership star for the Hawthorn Hawks, he survived a hell of a lot of adversity with some very serious cancer scares and handled himself with nothing but grace and dignity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a Linear Regression Model in R to Predict AFL Crowds</title>
      <link>/blog/building-a-linear-regression-model-in-r-to-predict-afl-crowds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/building-a-linear-regression-model-in-r-to-predict-afl-crowds/</guid>
      <description>Introduction There is a lot of talk about crowd behaviour and crowd issues with the modern day AFL. I personally feel the crowd issues are a case of business-as-usual; I’ve been going to AFL games on-and-off for close to three decades and the crowd behaviour is no different today as it was 20 years ago… just now everyone with a phone and Twitter account is a journo.
Anyway, that’s my two cents worth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Data To Determine Which AFL Fans Jump On The Bandwagon</title>
      <link>/blog/using-data-to-determine-which-afl-fans-jump-onthe-bandwagon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/using-data-to-determine-which-afl-fans-jump-onthe-bandwagon/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This post is the first in a two-part series on AFL crowds. This analysis will be a thorough look at AFL crowd numbers over the last 20 years, and will aim to discover which team’s fans are the biggest bandwagon jumpers. Bandwagon Jumpers are those fans that are the loudest in the office or in your friendship group when things are going well, and the quietest when their team is losing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is Jason Zivkovic and I&amp;rsquo;m a Data Scientist at the Reece Group.
Growing up as a sports-mad child and teen, statistics were always in my world. But with the love of sport blinding me, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even realise it was a love of statistics and data. Then, after meandering (much to my mother&amp;rsquo;s chagrin) through my early work life, and dabbling with different careers, I discovered edX and DataCamp and the data analysis short courses they had available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects Page</title>
      <link>/projects/about_projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/projects/about_projects/</guid>
      <description>This page is designed to collate all projects I&amp;rsquo;ve either contributed to or built myself.
TBC</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>