<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tidyverse on Don&#39;t Blame The Data</title>
    <link>/tags/tidyverse/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tidyverse on Don&#39;t Blame The Data</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/tidyverse/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>An In Depth Analysis of FIFA 19</title>
      <link>/blog/an-in-depth-analysis-of-fifa19/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/an-in-depth-analysis-of-fifa19/</guid>
      <description>This post was originally released on the Kaggle FIFA 19 Complete Player dataset that was kindly collected by Karan Gadiya. Many thanks Karan. The link to my original kernel is here
The full code base can be found here
Introduction From Wikipedia:
 FIFA 19 is a football simulation video game developed by EA Vancouver as part of Electronic Arts’ FIFA series. Announced on 6 June 2018 for its E3 2018 press conference, it was released on 28 September 2018 for PlayStation 3, PlayStation 4, Xbox 360, Xbox One, Nintendo Switch, and Microsoft Windows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tribute to Jarryd Roughead with some obscure data</title>
      <link>/blog/a-tribute-to-jarryd-roughead-using-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-tribute-to-jarryd-roughead-using-data-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Jarryd Roughead - four-time Hawthorn premiership player and all round great man - formally announced his retirement this week, with his last game coming over the weekend against the Gold Coast Suns.
Not only was he a pivotal four-time premiership star for the Hawthorn Hawks, he survived a hell of a lot of adversity with some very serious cancer scares and handled himself with nothing but grace and dignity.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>