<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>afl on Don&#39;t Blame The Data</title>
    <link>/categories/afl/</link>
    <description>Recent content in afl on Don&#39;t Blame The Data</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/afl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Effectively Simplifying AFL Tipping</title>
      <link>/blog/simplifying-afl-tipping/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/simplifying-afl-tipping/</guid>
      <description>I feel like I always overthink footy tipping. During each round, I make myself believe I have some sort of secret sauce and conjure up visions in my head of nailing a solid roughy… and then fall flat half way through the season and give up…
So then I thought, surely there’s an easier way. Only problem was, I thought this up last weekend (during the last season of the round)…</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tribute to Jarryd Roughead with some obscure data</title>
      <link>/blog/a-tribute-to-jarryd-roughead-using-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-tribute-to-jarryd-roughead-using-data-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Jarryd Roughead - four-time Hawthorn premiership player and all round great man - formally announced his retirement this week, with his last game coming over the weekend against the Gold Coast Suns.
Not only was he a pivotal four-time premiership star for the Hawthorn Hawks, he survived a hell of a lot of adversity with some very serious cancer scares and handled himself with nothing but grace and dignity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a Linear Regression Model in R to Predict AFL Crowds</title>
      <link>/blog/building-a-linear-regression-model-in-r-to-predict-afl-crowds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/building-a-linear-regression-model-in-r-to-predict-afl-crowds/</guid>
      <description>Introduction There is a lot of talk about crowd behaviour and crowd issues with the modern day AFL. I personally feel the crowd issues are a case of business-as-usual; I’ve been going to AFL games on-and-off for close to three decades and the crowd behaviour is no different today as it was 20 years ago… just now everyone with a phone and Twitter account is a journo.
Anyway, that’s my two cents worth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Data To Determine Which AFL Fans Jump On The Bandwagon</title>
      <link>/blog/using-data-to-determine-which-afl-fans-jump-onthe-bandwagon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/using-data-to-determine-which-afl-fans-jump-onthe-bandwagon/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This post is the first in a two-part series on AFL crowds. This analysis will be a thorough look at AFL crowd numbers over the last 20 years, and will aim to discover which team’s fans are the biggest bandwagon jumpers. Bandwagon Jumpers are those fans that are the loudest in the office or in your friendship group when things are going well, and the quietest when their team is losing.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>